<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Laurie Louise Baker</title>
    <link>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Laurie Baker, 2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/images/icon_hue23dc9bb0d93d4d3ad76535bef8e6086_9770442_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fisheries</title>
      <link>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/congrio-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/congrio-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I studied the factors influencing a fisher&amp;rsquo;s catch intention in the Chilean industrial longline fishery for which I was awarded the Margaret Lang Award for best undergraduate dissertation in Marine Biology at the University of St. Andrews. In the same year, I was awarded a small ecological project grant from the British Ecological Society to visit Dr. Rodrigo Wiff at the Instituto de Fomento Pesquero in Valparaíso and Claudio Gatica at the Instituto de Investigación Pesquera (INPESCA) in Talcahuano, Chile to study the reproductive ecology of the female pink cusk-eel (&lt;em&gt;Genypterus blacodes&lt;/em&gt;: Congrio dorado).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the four months I spent in Chile, I participated in a range of field work including aboard a 50m trawler fishing off the coast of Concepción for humboldt squid (&lt;em&gt;Dosidicus gigas&lt;/em&gt;: Jibia) and 3 days aboard an artisanal vessel in Chiloé fishing for Chilean King Crab (&lt;em&gt;Lithodes santolla&lt;/em&gt;: Centolla).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;congrio_centolla.jpg&#34; alt = &#34;Congrio and Centolla on the Rainbow Warrior&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the Scottish Haggis, Congrio Dorado has a famous &amp;ldquo;Ode&amp;rdquo; written about it by one of Chile&amp;rsquo;s most famous poets, Pablo Neruda 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.neruda.uchile.cl/obra/obraodaselementales2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Oda al Caldillo de Congrio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grey Seals on the Scotian Shelf</title>
      <link>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/bioprobe-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/bioprobe-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R building blocks for mapping data in Africa</title>
      <link>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/afrimapr-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/afrimapr-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Together with afrimapr I have been building an open access interactive learnr tutorial, &lt;strong&gt;afrijoin&lt;/strong&gt; on spatial joins in R. You can track our progress on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/afrimapr/afrijoin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;afrijoin_preview.PNG&#34; alt = &#34;Preview of our interactive learnr tutorial afrijoin which covers spatial joins in R&#34;&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outfoxing Rabies</title>
      <link>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/rabies-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/project/rabies-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rabies is a deadly viral infection that kills over 50,000 people each year. Mass vaccination can greatly reduce the burden of vaccine-preventable diseases such as rabies, however, there is relatively little scientific guidance as to how long control programmes must operate and how they should be best implemented to achieve elimination. My PhD and Postdoc focused on two pivotal questions in infectious disease ecology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the underlying determinants of disease persistence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can vaccination strategies be optimised to eliminate infection?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, I analysed a rich and highly resolved spatial dataset of fox rabies cases and oral rabies vaccination (ORV) programmes throughout Western Europe. The long-term, large-scale nature of these data provides a unique opportunity to improve our understanding of wildlife rabies dynamics in response to vaccination using novel spatial modeling techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I developed a cutting-edge hierarchical Bayesian state-space model that incorporates process and
observation uncertainty to study fox rabies persistence
in response to the timing of vaccination campaigns
over the last 30 years in Germany
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lauriebaker.rbind.io/publication/plos-article/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Baker et al. 2020)&lt;/a&gt;. I then used this
model to explore the optimal timing of vaccination
campaigns and the impact of missed campaigns on
the time required to eliminate the disease through
simulation 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lauriebaker.rbind.io/publication/phil-trans-article/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Baker et al. 2019)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my PhD and Postdoc, I collaborated with Prof. ‪Håvard Rue ‬at the Norwegian University of Science and Technology (NTNU) and King
Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST) and Dr. Elias Krainski from the Universidade Federal do Paraná (UFPR) in Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my MRC fellowship I developed a local 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lauriebaker.rbind.io/publication/conference-paper/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;spatiotemporal model&lt;/a&gt; of fox rabies dynamics fit to the GPS locations of rabies cases using a stochastic partial differential equation (SPDE) approach in the integrated nested Laplace approximation (INLA) framework. By simultaneously modeling the spatial and temporal dynamics of disease spread, I was able to capture key aspects of rabies dynamics to inform ongoing vaccination campaigns in Eastern Europe and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
